A Guide to the Virginia Canals and Navigations Society Records, 1966-2009
Library of Virginia
Library of Virginia
Virginia Canals and Navigations Society Records, 1966-2009
The Library of Virginia
36741
14.5 cubic feet (33 boxes)
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
Gift of Philip L. Eckman, Virginia Canals and Navigations Society, Richmond.
Historical Information
The Virginia Canals and Navigations Society was formed in 1977 to preserve and enhance Virginia's rich inland waterways heritage in all its aspects, including history, exploration, archaeology, modeling, local lore and legend, restoration, preservation, park and trail development. The Society became organized in 1980 with a constitution, by-laws, and elected trustees. In 1982 it was chartered by the state as a non-stock corporation, and by the federal government as a non-profit organization. Its headquarters are in Alexandria, Virginia.
Scope and Content
Records, 1966-2009, of the Virginia Canals and Navigations Society, including correspondence, financial records, minutes, reports, meeting information, membership lists, President's papers, newsletters, publications, project files, photographs, and clippings.
The VCNS FOUNDING PAPERS include biographies of some of the founders of the Society, its constitution, by-laws, and charter, and IRS information. The VCNS HISTORIC FILES contain policy statement, annual meeting files, membership rosters, Board meeting minutes, files of former presidents of the Society, including Robert O. Bush, George W. Higgs, Jr., William E. Trout III, Samuel L. Hopper, Myles R. Howlett, Vivienne Mitchell, Wyn Price, Nancy Dunnavant, and Ruth P. Harris. There is a substantial amount of information on the Patowmack Canal near Great Falls, Virginia. This series also includes treasurer's files containing correspondence, bills, receipts, account information, balance sheets, and treasurer's reports, as well as archivists' files, copies of the Society's newsletter, trustee's files, information on various chapters, certificates of appreciation, and special events material. The VCNS PUBLICATIONS series includes copies of various pamphlets, atlases, books, and leaflets published by the Society, including its magazine, "THE TILLER."
The VCNS PROJECTS series contains information on projects in which the Society was active, including restoration projects, festivals, a film on the James River, an essay contest, development of its Web page, riverfront development projects, the disposition of its archives, and outreach. The VIRGINIA WATERWAYS REGISTER files contain information on locks, dams, and canals that were nominated for the National Register of Historic Places, as well as material on the status of Virginia canals. The OTHER SOURCE INFO series includes copies of bibliographies on canals from other institutions, exhibit information, a shelf list of the James River and Kanawha Canal Library Collection, directories, and other reference sources. The MANUSCRIPT COLLECTION contains copies of manuscripts, essays, and other canal-related documents from various institutions.
The CANAL SOCIETIES PERIODICALS series consists of periodicals from other canal societies throughout the United States and Canada. The VIRGINIA CANALS AND RIVERS series includes published articles, brochures, pamphlets, maps, and other information on various canals and rivers in the state. Similar information can be found in the U.S. AND FOREIGN CANALS series.
Also included in this collection are photographs of models, dioramas, and displays put together by the Society, as well as canal-related prints and music, clippings, ephemera, and miscellaneous publications.
Arrangement
This collection is arranged into the following record groups, based on the original order and numbering system:
R.G. 0. Founding Papers.
R.G. 1. Historic Files.
R.G. 2. Publications.
R.G. 3. Projects.
R.G. 4. Virginia Waterways Register.
R.G. 5. Other Source Info.
R.G. 6. Manuscript Collection.
R.G. 7. Photograph Collection.
R.G. 8. Canal Societies Periodicals.
R.G. 9. Virginia Canals and Rivers.
R.G. 10. U.S. and Foreign Canals.
R.G. 11. Models/Dioramas Collection.
R.G. 12. Archaelogical Artifacts.
R.G. 13. Artworks Collection.
R.G. 14. Map Collection.
R.G. 15. Newspaper Clippings.
R.G. 16. Video Collection.
R.G. 17. Ephemera Collection.
R.G. 18. Special Collections.
Contents List
- R.G. 0-1 - Founders' Biographies - Higgs, George W., Jr. (Box 1, Folder 1)
- R.G. 0-1 - Founders' Biographies - Trout, William E. III. (Box 1, Folder 2)
- R.G. 0-1 - Founders' Biographies - Rich Davis (Founders Papers). (Box 1, Folder 3)
- R.G. 0-1 - Founders' Biographies - Harding, Russell (Founders Papers). (Box 1, Folder 4)
- R.G. 0-2 - Organizing Committee. (Box 1, Folder 5)
- R.G. 0-3 - Contitution, By-Laws, Charter - Proposed Changes to Constitution. (Box 1, Folder 6)
- R.G. 0-3 - Contitution, By-Laws, Charter. (Box 1, Folder 7-8)
- R.G. 0-4 - IRS Tax Status - IRS Report, 17 May 1990. (Box 1, Folder 9)
- R.G. 0-4 - IRS/Taxes, 1981-1990. (Box 1, Folder 10)
- R.G. 1-0 - Policy Statements. (Box 1, Folder 11)
- R.G. 1-1 - Annual General Meeting - Richmond, 1978. (Box 1, Folder 12)
- R.G. 1-1 - Annual General Meeting - Warrenton, 1979. (Box 1, Folder 13)
- R.G. 1-1 - Annual General Meeting - Great Falls, 1980. (Box 1, Folder 14)
- R.G. 1-1 - Annual General Meeting - Lynchburg, 1981. (Box 1, Folder 15)
- R.G. 1-1 - Annual General Meeting - Newport News, 1982. (Box 1, Folder 16)
- R.G. 1-1 - Annual General Meeting - Lexington, 1983. (Box 1, Folder 17)
- R.G. 1-1 - Annual General Meeting - Fluvanna County, 1984. (Box 1, Folder 18)
- R.G. 1-1 - Annual General Meeting - Richmond, 1985. (Box 1, Folder 19)
- R.G. 1-1 - Annual General Meeting - Lynchburg, 1986. (Box 1, Folder 20)
- R.G. 1-1 - Annual General Meeting - Alexandria/Great Falls, 1987. (Box 1, Folder 21)
- R.G. 1-1 - Annual General Meeting - Fredericksburg, 1988. (Box 1, Folder 22)
- R.G. 1-1 - Annual General Meeting - Buchanan, 1989. (Box 1, Folder 23)
- R.G. 1-1 - Annual General Meeting - Petersburg, 1990. (Box 2, Folder 1)
- R.G. 1-1 - Annual General Meeting - Goose Creek/Leesburg, 1991. (Box 2, Folder 2)
- R.G. 1-1 - Annual General Meeting - Roanoke Rapids, NC, 1992. (Box 2, Folder 3)
- R.G. 1-1 - Annual General Meeting - Dismal Swamp, 1993. (Box 2, Folder 4)
- R.G. 1-1 - Annual General Meeting - Harpers Ferry, WV, 1994. (Box 2, Folder 5)
- R.G. 1-1 - Annual General Meeting - Roanoke, 1995. (Box 2, Folder 6)
- R.G. 1-1 - Annual General Meeting - Goochland, 1996. (Box 2, Folder 7)
- R.G. 1-1 - Annual General Meeting - Northern Virginia/C & O Canal, 1997. (Box 2, Folder 8)
- R.G. 1-1 - Annual General Meeting - Rivanna River/Charlottesville, 1998. (Box 2, Folder 9)
- R.G. 1-1 - Annual General Meeting - Lexington, 1999. (Box 2, Folder 10)
- R.G. 1-1 - Annual General Meeting - Richmond, 2000. (Box 2, Folder 11)
- R.G. 1-1 - Annual General Meeting - Fredericksburg, 2001. (Box 2, Folder 12)
- R.G. 1-1 - Annual General Meeting - Scottsville, 2002. (Box 2, Folder 13)
- R.G. 1-1 - Annual General Meeting - Danville, 2003. (Box 2, Folder 14)
- R.G. 1-1 - Annual General Meeting - Chesapeake, 2005. (Box 2, Folder 15)
- R.G. 1-1 - Annual General Meeting - Roanoke Rapids, NC, 2006. (Box 2, Folder 16)
- R.G. 1-1 - Annual General Meeting - Petersburg, 2007. (Box 2, Folder 17)
- R.G. 1-1 - Annual General Meeting - Wakefield, 2008. (Box 2, Folder 18)
- R.G. 1-2 - Membership Rosters, 1979-1980. (Box 2, Folder 19)
- R.G. 1-2 - Membership Rosters, 1981-1985. (Box 2, Folder 20)
- R.G. 1-2 - Membership Rosters, 1986-1990. (Box 2, Folder 21)
- R.G. 1-2 - Membership Rosters, 1991-1995. (Box 3, Folder 1)
- R.G. 1-2 - Membership Rosters, 1996-2000. (Box 3, Folder 2)
- R.G. 1-2 - Membership Rosters, 2001-2008. (Box 3, Folder 3)
- R.G. 1-3 - Board Meeting Minutes, 1979-1980. (Box 3, Folder 4)
- R.G. 1-3 - Board Meeting Minutes, 1981-1985. (Box 3, Folder 5)
- R.G. 1-3 - Board Meeting Minutes, 1986-1990. (Box 3, Folder 6)
- R.G. 1-3 - Board Meeting Minutes, 1991-1995. (Box 3, Folder 7)
- R.G. 1-3 - Board Meeting Minutes, 1996-2000. (Box 3, Folder 8-9)
- R.G. 1-3 - Board Meeting Minutes, 2001-2008. (Box 3, Folder 10)
- R.G. 1-3 - Board Meeting Minutes - Summary of Activities Extracted from the Minutes of the Board of Governors/Directors' Meetings, 1979-1998. (Box 3, Folder 11)
- R.G. 1-4 - President's Files (Bush, Robert O.) - Correspondence - General Incoming, 1977-1980. (Box 3, Folder 12)
- R.G. 1-4 - President's Files (Bush, Robert O.) - Hobbs, Gibson (Lynchburg). (Box 3, Folder 13)
- R.G. 1-4 - President's Files (Bush, Robert O.) - Fletcher, Richard R. (Rockbridge Co.) (Box 3, Folder 14)
- R.G. 1-4 - President's Files (Bush, Robert O.) - Trout, William E. III. (Box 3, Folder 15)
- R.G. 1-4 - President's Files (Bush, Robert O.) - Membership Growth (Box 3, Folder 16)
- R.G. 1-4 - President's Files (Bush, Robert O.) - Miscellaneous Canal Information 1977-1980. (Box 4, Folder 1)
- R.G. 1-4 - President's Files (Bush, Robert O.) - Parkinson, William W. (Warrenton) 1977-1980. (Box 4, Folder 2)
- R.G. 1-4 - President's Files (Bush, Robert O.) - Outgoing Correspondence. (Box 4, Folder 3)
- R.G. 1-4 - President's Files (Bush, Robert O.) - VCNS Fouding, Special Notices, Rosters. (Box 4, Folder 4)
- R.G. 1-4 - President's Files (Higgs, George W., Jr.) - National Park Service Legislation and Regulations. (Box 4, Folder 5)
- R.G. 1-4 - President's Files (Higgs, George W., Jr.) - Potomac Canal Talk and Slide Show. (Box 4, Folder 6)
- R.G. 1-4 - President's Files (Higgs, George W., Jr.) - Meetings. (Box 4, Folder 7)
- R.G. 1-4 - President's Files (Higgs, George W., Jr.) - Bazuin, Sybil. (Box 4, Folder 8)
- R.G. 1-4 - President's Files (Higgs, George W., Jr.) - Alexandria Canal. (Box 4, Folder 9)
- R.G. 1-4 - President's Files (Higgs, George W., Jr.) - Haxall, Theodore (Boats). (Box 4, Folder 10)
- R.G. 1-4 - President's Files (Higgs, George W., Jr.) - Bush, Bob. (Box 4, Folder 11)
- R.G. 1-4 - President's Files (Higgs, George W., Jr.) - Lewis, John G.. (Box 4, Folder 12)
- R.G. 1-4 - President's Files (Higgs, George W., Jr.) - Public Relations. (Box 4, Folder 13)
- R.G. 1-4 - President's Files (Higgs, George W., Jr.) - Shank, Bill - American Canal Society. (Box 4, Folder 14)
- R.G. 1-4 - President's Files (Higgs, George W., Jr.) - Arlington County. (Box 4, Folder 15)
- R.G. 1-4 - President's Files (Higgs, George W., Jr.) - Fairfax County. (Box 4, Folder 16)
- R.G. 1-4 - President's Files (Higgs, George W., Jr.) - Patowmack Canal - Archaelogical Reports. (Box 4, Folder 17)
- R.G. 1-4 - President's Files (Higgs, George W., Jr.) - Great Falls - Patowmack Canal. (Box 4, Folder 18)
- R.G. 1-4 - President's Files (Higgs, George W., Jr.) - Antiquity Act Permit - Patowmack Canal. (Box 4, Folder 19)
- R.G. 1-4 - President's Files (Higgs, George W., Jr.) - Bush, Bob. (Box 4, Folder 20)
- R.G. 1-4 - President's Files (Higgs, George W., Jr.) - Harbaugh Journal. (Box 4, Folder 21)
- R.G. 1-4 - President's Files (Higgs, George W., Jr.) - Annual Meetings. (Box 4, Folder 22)
- R.G. 1-4 - President's Files (Higgs, George W., Jr.) - Virginia Constitution Bicentennial Commission. (Box 4, Folder 23)
- R.G. 1-4 - President's Files (Higgs, George W., Jr.) - Pennsylvania Canal Society Spring Tour at Potomac Canal, 1995. (Box 4, Folder 24)
- R.G. 1-4 - President's Files (Higgs, George W., Jr.) - Great Falls Park GIS Map - Index. (Box 5, Folder 1)
- R.G. 1-4 - President's Files (Higgs, George W., Jr.) - Patowmack Canal Workshop, 4-5 May 1983. (Box 5, Folder 2)
- R.G. 1-4 - President's Files (Higgs, George W., Jr.) - Patowmack Canal Correspondence to W. E. Trout. (Box 5, Folder 3)
- R.G. 1-4 - President's Files (Higgs, George W., Jr.) - Patowmack Canal Congressional Correspondence. (Box 5, Folder 4)
- R.G. 1-4 - President's Files (Higgs, George W., Jr.) - Patowmack Canal - Fitzsimons, Neal. (Box 5, Folder 5)
- R.G. 1-4 - President's Files (Higgs, George W., Jr.) - Patowmack Canal - Hobbs, Gibson. (Box 5, Folder 6)
- R.G. 1-4 - President's Files (Higgs, George W., Jr.) - Patowmack Canal - Warner, Sen. John. (Box 5, Folder 7)
- R.G. 1-4 - President's Files (Higgs, George W., Jr.) - Patowmack Canal - Trible, Sen. Paul. (Box 5, Folder 8)
- R.G. 1-4 - President's Files (Higgs, George W., Jr.) - Patowmack Canal - Great Falls Historical Society. (Box 5, Folder 9)
- R.G. 1-4 - President's Files (Higgs, George W., Jr.) - Patowmack Canal - Parris, Stan. (Box 5, Folder 10)
- R.G. 1-4 - President's Files (Higgs, George W., Jr.) - Patowmack Canal - National Park Service Proposals. (Box 5, Folder 11)
- R.G. 1-4 - President's Files (Higgs, George W., Jr.) - Patowmack Canal - National Park Service. (Box 5, Folder 12-13)
- R.G. 1-4 - President's Files (Higgs, George W., Jr.) - Patowmack Canal - Stock Ledger, National Archives. (Box 5, Folder 14)
- R.G. 1-4 - President's Files (Higgs, George W., Jr.) - Patowmack Canal - Northern Virginia Association of Historians. (Box 5, Folder 15)
- R.G. 1-4 - President's Files (Higgs, George W., Jr.) - Patowmack Canal - ASCE History and Heritage Committee. (Box 5, Folder 16)
- R.G. 1-4 - President's Files (Higgs, George W., Jr.) - Patowmack Canal - McGrail, Thomas H.. (Box 5, Folder 17)
- R.G. 1-4 - President's Files (Higgs, George W., Jr.) - Patowmack Canal - Iaccoca, Lee. (Box 6, Folder 1)
- R.G. 1-4 - President's Files (Higgs, George W., Jr.) - Patowmack Canal - Restoration II. (Box 6, Folder 2)
- R.G. 1-4 - President's Files (Higgs, George W., Jr.) - Potomac Canal Basin Consortium. (Box 6, Folder 3)
- R.G. 1-4 - President's Files (Higgs, George W., Jr.) - Patowmack Canal - ASCE Meetings and Reports. (Box 6, Folder 4)
- R.G. 1-4 - President's Files (Higgs, George W., Jr.) - Patowmack Canal - Virginia Society of Professional Engineers. (Box 6, Folder 5)
- R.G. 1-4 - President's Files (Higgs, George W., Jr.) - Patowmack Canal - Various Government Agencies. (Box 6, Folder 6)
- R.G. 1-4 - President's Files (Higgs, George W., Jr.) - Batteau Fest (Joe Ayers). (Box 6, Folder 7)
- R.G. 1-4 - President's Files (Higgs, George W., Jr.) - John Lewis - Goose Creek. (Box 6, Folder 8)
- R.G. 1-4 - President's Files (Higgs, George W., Jr.) - Patowmack Canal - Correspondence and Reports. (Box 6, Folder 9-10)
- R.G. 1-4 - President's Files (Higgs, George W., Jr.) - Burke Dam. (Box 6, Folder 11)
- R.G. 1-4 - President's Files (Higgs, George W., Jr.) - Gude, Gilbert. (Box 6, Folder 12)
- R.G. 1-4 - President's Files (Higgs, George W., Jr.) - Essay Contest - "From Canal to Constitution". (Box 6, Folder 13)
- R.G. 1-4 - President's Files (Higgs, George W., Jr.) - Speech to Northern Virginia Regional Park Authority. (Box 6, Folder 14)
- R.G. 1-4 - President's Files (Higgs, George W., Jr.) - Donation Campaign - Buchanan Flood, 1985. (Box 6, Folder 15)
- R.G. 1-4 - President's Files (Higgs, George W., Jr.) - Miscellaneous. (Box 6, Folder 16)
- R.G. 1-4 - President's Files (Trout, William E. III) - Annual Meeting, 1984. (Box 7, Folder 1-2)
- R.G. 1-4 - President's Files (Trout, William E. III) - FFV (Float Fishermen of Virginia). (Box 7, Folder 3)
- R.G. 1-4 - President's Files (Trout, William E. III) - Virginia List of Rivers. (Box 7, Folder 4)
- R.G. 1-4 - President's Files (Trout, William E. III) - Virginia List of Rivers. (Box 7, Folder 4)
- R.G. 1-4 - President's Files (Trout, William E. III) - Harding, Russ. (Box 7, Folder 5-8)
- R.G. 1-4 - President's Files (Trout, William E. III) - Virginia List of Rivers. (Box 7, Folder 4)
- R.G. 1-4 - President's Files (Trout, William E. III) - Virginia List of Rivers. (Box 7, Folder 4)
- R.G. 1-4 - President's Files (Trout, William E. III) - Fluvanna Meeting, 1984. (Box 7, Folder 9)
- R.G. 1-4 - President's Files (Trout, William E. III) - VCNS Flyer. (Box 7, Folder 10-11)
- R.G. 1-4 - President's Files (Trout, William E. III) - VCNS Logo. (Box 8, Folder 1)
- R.G. 1-4 - President's Files (Trout, William E. III) - VCNS. (Box 8, Folder 2-10)
- R.G. 1-4 - President's Files (Trout, William E. III) - Miscellaneous. (Box 8, Folder 11-12)
- R.G. 1-4 - President's Files (Howlett, Myles R.) - Reports and Correspondence from W.E. Trout III. (Box 9, Folder 1)
- R.G. 1-4 - President's Files (Howlett, Myles R.) - Incoming Correspondence, 1988-1995. (Box 9, Folder 2)
- R.G. 1-4 - President's Files (Howlett, Myles R.) - Canal Restoration Commentary (Morant). (Box 9, Folder 3)
- R.G. 1-4 - President's Files (Howlett, Myles R.) - Canal Conferences. (Box 9, Folder 4)
- R.G. 1-4 - President's Files (Howlett, Myles R.) - Patowmack Canal Restoration. (Box 9, Folder 5-8)
- R.G. 1-4 - President's Files (Howlett, Myles R.) - Essay Contest - "From Canal to Constitution". (Box 9, Folder 9)
- R.G. 1-4 - President's Files (Howlett, Myles R.) - Miscellaneous. (Box 9, Folder 10)
- R.G. 1-4 - President's Files (Mitchell, Vivienne) - Miscellaneous. (Box 10, Folder 1-3)
- R.G. 1-4 - President's Files (Price, Wyn) - Miscellaneous. (Box 10, Folder 4)
- R.G. 1-4 - President's Files (Dunnavant, Nancy R.) - Miscellaneous. (Box 10, Folder 5)
- R.G. 1-4 - President's Files (Harris, Ruth P.) - Miscellaneous. (Box 10, Folder 6)
- R.G. 1-4 - President's Files (Kastner, Thomas M.) - Miscellaneous. (Box 10, Folder 7-9)
- R.G. 1-6 - Treasurer's Files - Bank (Bob Bush), 1978-1980. (Box 11, Folder 1)
- R.G. 1-6 - Treasurer's Files - Savings Account, 4 June - 29 December 1980. (Box 11, Folder 2)
- R.G. 1-6 - Treasurer's Files - Balance Sheets, 1980-1990. (Box 11, Folder 3)
- R.G. 1-6 - Treasurer's Files - Checking Account, Bank Statements, Cancelled Checks, 1980-1986. (Box 11, Folder 4)
- R.G. 1-6 - Treasurer's Files - Bills and Receipts, 1981. (Box 11, Folder 5)
- R.G. 1-6 - Treasurer's Files - Bank Statements/Deposit Stubs, 1981-1982. (Box 11, Folder 6)
- R.G. 1-6 - Treasurer's Files - Bills and Receipts, 1982-1983. (Box 11, Folder 7)
- R.G. 1-6 - Treasurer's Files - Bank Statements, 1983-1984. (Box 11, Folder 8)
- R.G. 1-6 - Treasurer's Files - Savings Account, 1983-1986. (Box 11, Folder 9)
- R.G. 1-6 - Treasurer's Files - Bills and Receipts, 1984. (Box 11, Folder 10)
- R.G. 1-6 - Treasurer's Files - Insurance, 1985. (Box 11, Folder 11)
- R.G. 1-6 - Treasurer's Files - Bank, 1986. (Box 11, Folder 12)
- R.G. 1-6 - Treasurer's Files - Correspondence, 1986. (Box 11, Folder 13)
- R.G. 1-6 - Treasurer's Files - Receipts, 1986. (Box 12, Folder 1)
- R.G. 1-6 - Treasurer's Files - Cancelled Checks (1001-1242), 24 June 1986 - 24 July 1991. (Box 12, Folder 2-4)
- R.G. 1-6 - Treasurer's Files - Bank, 1987. (Box 12, Folder 5)
- R.G. 1-6 - Treasurer's Files - Correspondence, 1987. (Box 12, Folder 6)
- R.G. 1-6 - Treasurer's Files - Receipts, 1987. (Box 12, Folder 7)
- R.G. 1-6 - Treasurer's Files - Check Registers, 1987-1991. (Box 12, Folder 8)
- R.G. 1-6 - Treasurer's Files - Bank (First American Bank)/Seligman Group, 1988. (Box 12, Folder 9)
- R.G. 1-6 - Treasurer's Files - Correspondence, 1988. (Box 13, Folder 1-2)
- R.G. 1-6 - Treasurer's Files - Internal Revenue Service, 1988. (Box 13, Folder 3)
- R.G. 1-6 - Treasurer's Files - Receipts, 1988. (Box 13, Folder 4)
- R.G. 1-6 - Treasurer's Files - First American Bank/Seligman Group, 1989. (Box 13, Folder 5)
- R.G. 1-6 - Treasurer's Files - Correspondence, 1989. (Box 13, Folder 6)
- R.G. 1-6 - Treasurer's Files - Receipts, 1989. (Box 13, Folder 7)
- R.G. 1-6 - Treasurer's Files - Correspondence, 1990. (Box 13, Folder 8)
- R.G. 1-6 - Treasurer's Files - First American Bank/Seligman Group, 1990. (Box 13, Folder 9)
- R.G. 1-6 - Treasurer's Files - Receipts, 1990. (Box 13, Folder 10)
- R.G. 1-6 - Treasurer's Files - Membership Applications. (Box 13, Folder 11-12)
- R.G. 1-6 - Treasurer's Files - Reports, 1985-1989. (Box 14, Folder 1)
- R.G. 1-6 - Treasurer's Files - Reports, 1990-1998. (Box 14, Folder 2)
- R.G. 1-6 - Treasurer's Files - Reports, 1999-2001. (Box 14, Folder 3)
- R.G. 1-6 - Treasurer's Files - Howlett, Lynn 1985-1989. (Box 14, Folder 4)
- R.G. 1-6 - Treasurer's Files - Bank Statements. (Box 14, Folder 5)
- R.G. 1-6 - Treasurer's Files - First American Bank/Seligman Fund. (Box 14, Folder 6)
- R.G. 1-7 - Archivist's Files - Reports and Correspondence. (Box 14, Folder 7-11)
- R.G. 1-8 - "Tiller" Editor Files. (Box 15, Folder 1)
- R.G. 1-9 - Special Notices. (Box 15, Folder 2)
- R.G. 1-10 - "The Sweep" VCNS Newsletter, 1985-2000. (Box 15, Folder 3)
- R.G. 1-10 - "The Sweep" VCNS Newsletter, 2001-2007. (Box 15, Folder 4)
- R.G. 1-11 - Calendar of Events, 1997. (Box 15, Folder 5)
- R.G. 1-12 - VCNS Districts. (Box 15, Folder 6)
- R.G. 1-13 - Certificates of Appreciation. (Box 15, Folder 7)
- R.G. 1-13-1 - Memorials. (Box 15, Folder 8)
- R.G. 1-14 - Trustee's Files (Hobbs, Thomas Gibson, Jr.). (Box 15, Folder 9)
- R.G. 1-14 - Trustee's Files - Miscellaneous. (Box 15, Folder 10)
- R.G. 1-14 - Trustee's Files (McGehee, Minnie Lee) - Essays by William E. Trout III. (Box 15, Folder 11-13)
- R.G. 1-15 - VCNS Chapters. (Box 15, Folder 14)
- R.G. 1-15 - Potomac Chapter Meetings, 1986. (Box 15, Folder 15)
- R.G. 1-16 - Special Events. (Box 15, Folder 16)
- R.G. 1-17 - James River Batteau Festival - Agendas, Minutes, Financial Records, etc. (Box 15, Folder 17)
- R.G. 2-1 - Index to VCNS Publications. (Box 16, Folder 1)
- R.G. 2-2 - "The Tiller," vol. 1, no. 1 - vol. 24, no. 3 (Spring, 1980 - Fall, 2003). (Box 16, Folder 2-9)
- R.G. 2-2 - "The Tiller," vol. 25, no. 1 - vol. 30, no. 2 (Spring, 2004 - Summer, 2009). (Box 17, Folder 1-2)
- R.G. 2-2 - "The Tiller" - Index. (Box 17, Folder 3)
- R.G. 2-3 - "Headwaters to the Sea" Pamphlet. (Box 17, Folder 4)
- R.G. 2-4 - "Canal Parks in Old Virginia" Leaflet. (Box 17, Folder 5)
- R.G. 2-5 - "The Bateauman's Guide to the James". (Box 17, Folder 6)
- R.G. 2-6 - "Touring Richmond's Canal" Pamphlet. (Box 17, Folder 7)
- R.G. 2-7 - "The Aged Pilot Man" Pamphlet. (Box 17, Folder 8)
- R.G. 2-8 - "James River Batteau Festival Trail" Atlas. (Box 17, Folder 9)
- R.G. 2-9 - "A Guide to the Works of the James River and Kanawha Company". (Box 17, Folder 10)
- R.G. 2-10 - "The James River and Kanawha Canal - Guide from Byrd Park to Tidewater". (Box 17, Folder 11)
- R.G. 2-11 - "The Patowmack Canal" Pamphlet. (Box 17, Folder 12)
- R.G. 2-12 - "The Appomattox River Atlas". (Box 17, Folder 13)
- R.G. 2-13 - "The Maury River Atlas". (Box 17, Folder 14)
- R.G. 2-14 - "The Rappahannock Scenic River Atlas". (Box 17, Folder 15)
- R.G. 2-15 - "Appomattox River Seay Stories" Book. (Box 17, Folder 16)
- R.G. 2-16 - "The Rivanna River Atlas". (Box 17, Folder 17)
- R.G. 2-17 - "The Glorious Adventure" Pamphlet. (Box 17, Folder 18)
- R.G. 2-18 - "The Slate and Willis's Rivers Atlas". (Box 17, Folder 19)
- R.G. 2-19 - "The Goose Creek Scenic River Atlas". (Box 18, Folder 1)
- R.G. 2-20 - "The Dismal Swamp Canal Atlas". (Box 18, Folder 2)
- R.G. 2-20-1 - "The Dismal Swamp Canal Atlas" - Reprint. (Box 18, Folder 3)
- R.G. 2-21 - "The Upper James Atlas". (Box 18, Folder 4)
- R.G. 2-22 - "Goochland County's Historic Canals". (Box 18, Folder 5)
- R.G. 2-23 - "Fall of the James Atlas". (Box 18, Folder 6)
- R.G. 2-24 - "River Boat Echoes" Book. (Box 18, Folder 7)
- R.G. 2-25 - "Falls of the Appomattox Atlas". (Box 18, Folder 8)
- R.G. 2-26 - "The Patowmack Canal: From Canal to Constitution" Pamphlet. (Box 18, Folder 9)
- R.G. 2-27 - "The Shenandoah River Atlas". (Box 18, Folder 10)
- R.G. 2-28 - The Lockhouse at Nine Mile Locks. (Box 18, Folder 11)
- R.G. 2-29 - Stone Mileposts Along the Dismal Swamp Canal. (Box 18, Folder 12)
- R.G. 2-30 - "The Dan River Atlas". (Box 18, Folder 13)
- R.G. 2-31 - "The New River Atlas". (Box 18, Folder 14)
- R.G. 2-32 - "The Blackwater, Nottoway and Meherrin Rivers Atlas". (Box 18, Folder 15)
- R.G. 3-1 - VCNS Projects - Great Falls (Patowmack Canal) Restoration. (Box 19, Folder 1)
- R.G. 3-2 - VCNS Projects - James River Batteau Festival. (Box 19, Folder 2-3)
- R.G. 3-3 - VCNS Projects - Burke Dam Project. (Box 19, Folder 4)